"Onions and Tomatoes
Put to the Test for Osteoporosis
Feeding rats
dozens of different foods,
the fruit found to preserve
their bones the best
was the prune,
and the leading vegetable
was the onion.
I've talked already
about prunes.
What about onions?
The country with apparently
the highest per capita
consumption of onions
in the world is Turkey,
which also has
one of the lowest rates
of osteoporotic bone fractures.
Turkey may have
four times greater
daily per capita onion intake
than the United States
and four times lower hip
fracture probabilities.
Is that just
a coincidence, though?
The problem with
trying to correlate
country-by-country comparisons
is that you don't know if the
people within those countries
who are actually
eating those onions
are the ones who are actually
avoiding fractures.
But in 2017, a prospective
study was published
in which the fruit
and vegetable intake
of about 1,500 older women was
followed for nearly 15 years,
and of all of
the classes of vegetables,
the intake of
allium family veggies
such as onions,
leeks, and garlic
were the ones most associated
with lower risk
of bone fractures.
Based on a study of non-Hispanic
white women 50 years and older,
those who ate onions
on a daily basis
had an overall bone density
5 percent greater
than those who rarely ate them.
That may not sound like a lot
but could potentially
translate into reducing
the risk of hip fracture
by more than 20 percent.
Why onions?
Maybe it's the quercetin.
Onions are one of the
most concentrated sources
of this phytonutrient,
which can stimulate the activity
of our bone-building cells,
at least in a petri dish,
and is also a potent inhibitor
of the formation
of new bone-eating cells.
Or could it be
the fructan-fiber
prebiotics in onions?
Experimentally infused
into the rectum,
the short-chain fatty acids
created by our
fiber-eating gut flora
have been shown
to stimulate calcium absorption,
so much so that adolescents
randomized to the type
of fiber found in onions--
about an onion a day's worth
for a year--
significantly increased
their bone mineral density
over the placebo group.
In the rodent bone
preservation study,
a number of spices beat out
prunes and onions,
with the top dog being
another allium, garlic.
And, in the prospective
human study,
cruciferous vegetables
like broccoli
came in at a close second
to the allium family.
Although there are
some petri dish data
supporting the potential
bone benefits
of the sulforaphane
in cruciferous veggies,
inhibiting the formation
of bone-eating cells,
and it appears to protect
bone health in mice,
the reason
I'm singling out onions
is that it's one
of only two vegetables
that have actually been put
to the test in clinical trials.
But how are you going
to come up with a placebo onion
for the control group?
That's why a group of
innovative Chinese researchers
gave people onion juice
versus a fake onion juice.
I don't know which sounds worse,
but anything for science!
And, those randomized
to the real onion group
experienced an improvement
in a marker of bone loss
over the placebo,
but the study
didn't last long enough
to see if this translated
into tangible bone benefits.
But a clinical trial
on the other vegetable
put to the test did.
The tomato story starts out
like the onion story.
There's epidemiological support.
In the Framingham
Osteoporosis Study,
higher intakes of lycopene,
the red pigment in tomatoes,
were associated with
protection against bone loss
in older men and women
over a period of four years,
as well as protection
against hip fractures
over 17 years.
Perhaps this helps explain
why studies show
that increased adherence to
a more Mediterranean-style diet
is associated with about
20 percent fewer hip fractures.
Then there's
laboratory evidence.
Lycopene inhibits bone loss
in a petri dish
and preserves bone mass in rats.
However, so does
green tomato extract,
which is richer in compounds
such as tomatine
rather than lycopene,
so maybe there are multiple
protective factors in tomatoes.
Anyway, let's feed people
some tomato products
and see what happens!
Postmenopausal women
randomized to lycopene
in the form of about
a cup and a third of
regular tomato juice a day
experienced
a significant reduction
in a marker of bone loss
by month two,
and the opposite was
found after just a month
of restricting
lycopene consumption,
so, no tomatoes, watermelon,
or other red fruits
like pink grapefruit.
This suggests that just regular
dietary intakes are protective.
But does this translate
into retaining significantly
more bone over time?
Postmenopausal women given
about two-thirds of a cup
of tomato sauce a day
for three months
suffered significantly
less bone loss
than those in an age-matched
group who didn't,
though it does not appear
that the study subjects
were assigned randomly,
which could bias the results.
So, should we go out of our way
to include these specific fruits
and vegetables in our diet?
Normally, we're just left
with a "can't-hurt" shrug,
but a group
of New Zealand researchers
put together
a randomized controlled trial
to find out.
They developed
the Scarborough Fair Diet,
named for the presence
of presumptive
bone-protecting herbs parsley,
sage, rosemary, and thyme
from the song popularized
by Simon & Garfunkel.
The diet included prunes,
onions, and tomatoes.
They compared that
to a diet similarly packed
with nine or more servings
of fruits and vegetables,
but ones that were
not suspected as having
particularly
skeleton-saving properties.
Markers of bone turnover were
measured after three months,
and the specially concocted
diet of bone-preserving produce
did no significantly better
than the diet packed with
non-bone preserving produce,
or a diet with just six servings
of fruits and veggies a day,
suggesting that
the focus should just be on
stuffing your face with fruits
and vegetables of any stripe.